<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Eric Rochester</title>
    <link href="http://www.ericrochester.com//atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://www.ericrochester.com/" />
    <id>http://www.ericrochester.com//atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Eric Rochester</name>
        <email>erochest@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2017-04-12T10:29:24Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Hope</title>
    <link href="http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/thoughts/hope/index.html" />
    <id>http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/thoughts/hope/index.html</id>
    <published>2017-04-12T10:29:24Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-12T10:29:24Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I ran across this quote the other day listening to an <a href="https://onbeing.org/programs/joanna-macy-a-wild-love-for-the-world/">On Being interview with Joanna Macy</a>, and it reminded me of several separate discussions I’ve had over the last year about <em>hope</em>. The discussions were overlapping, but isolated, and each flavored and nuanced very differently, depending on whom I was talking with.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>For some reason this quote seemed an appropriate epilogue to these conversations, and it particularly resonates with me now, where I am as an individual and living in this country.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>MS. MACY</strong>: … I’m not insisting that we be brimming with hope. It’s OK not to be optimistic. Buddhist teachings say feeling that you have to maintain hope can wear you out. So just be present.</p>
<p><strong>MS. TIPPETT</strong>: [laughs] That’s good. Yes.</p>
<p><strong>MS. MACY</strong>: The biggest gift you can give is to be absolutely present, and when you’re worrying about whether you’re hopeful, or hopeless, or pessimistic, or optimistic, who cares? The main thing is that you’re showing up, that you’re here, and that you’re finding ever more capacity to love this world because it will not be healed without that. That was what is going to unleash our intelligence and our ingenuity and our solidarity for the healing of our world.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Long Haul</title>
    <link href="http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/activism/the-long-haul/index.html" />
    <id>http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/activism/the-long-haul/index.html</id>
    <published>2017-02-02T02:38:32Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-02T02:38:32Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I mentioned back in <a href="/posts/notes/pace-yourself/">“Pace Yourself”</a> that this is going to be a long four years. Lately, particularly after this first week, it really, really feels like it.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>I’ve been thinking over <a href="https://medium.com/the-coffeelicious/how-to-stayoutraged-without-losing-your-mind-fc0c41aa68f3">“How to #StayOutraged Without Losing Your Mind”</a> a lot lately as I’ve been watching this dumpster fire. This is a great resource. How does this become “normal” without reacting to it as normal?</p>
<p>One thing I’m trying to do is to look at the situation from all sides. I’m partway through <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/52397.Parable_of_the_Sower"><em>Parable of the Sower</em></a> by Octavia E. Butler. It’s a good pick. It feels right for the moment.</p>
<p>But next I think I’m going to read <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/4069.Man_s_Search_for_Meaning"><em>Man’s Search for Meaning</em></a> by Viktor E. Frankl. (I wonder if they have the same middle name?) I need to remember that those situations where people are at their worse are also the situations where people are at their best.</p>
<p>A couple of thoughts from the “#StayOutraged” post: Look away. We don’t want our eyes to get used to this.</p>
<p>And it mentions using one of the daily action lists that are going around as a way to make engaging easy. (If anyone has a favorite, please send it to me, and I’ll list it here.)</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://dailyaction.org/">Daily Action</a> Texts you an issue every day that you can call and speak out to a legislator on.</li>
</ul>
<p>It seems like looking away and daily action can work together. I’m more likely to give myself permission to look away if I am intentionally doing something small every day. It also mentioned that these lists can help make doing something fun.</p>
<p>Speaking of fun, I’ll leave you with this list of <a href="https://www.mcsweeneys.net/articles/concrete-actions-progressives-can-take-during-trumps-presidency">“Concrete Actions Progressives Can Take During Trump’s Presidency.”</a> Ouch.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>#FlipTheScript</title>
    <link href="http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/thoughts/flip-the-script/index.html" />
    <id>http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/thoughts/flip-the-script/index.html</id>
    <published>2017-01-18T19:53:36Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-18T19:53:36Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve almost let National Adoption Month go by without comment.</p>
<p>But I can’t.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>When we were waiting to adopt our first oldest, a lot of the other people we met who were also waiting were reading adoptive mommy blogs. Think mommy blogs with a pretty saccharine adoption narrative. Those didn’t feel real to me, so instead I read adoptee blogs. The adoptive parent blogs usually referred to these as “angry adoptees.”</p>
<p>Their perspectives felt better grounded in reality.</p>
<p>It was one of the best ways I could have prepared for being an adoptive parent.</p>
<p>Maybe they are angry. But only in the best way, of being angry at the injustices of the current system and speaking out about it.</p>
<p>Looking around to gather links for this post, I have realized that I don’t listen to these voices as much as I would like to. (I think part of it is that now I primarily listen haphazardly on Twitter.)</p>
<p>I have also realized that a lot of voices that were important in my journey on this have now gone silent. I wish them well and hope that they are leading beautiful lives.</p>
<p>Anyway, here are some adoptee voices that have been personally influential. They’re not all always talking about adoption, but most do sometimes. (Since I’m mainly listening to these voices on Twitter lately, I’ve decided to list Twitter accounts, where available, not blogs.)</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/AmandaTDA">Amanda</a> is a social worker, consultant, and therapist. She also founded Lost Daughters, listed below.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/theadoptedlife">Angela</a> has a YouTube channel and a documentary on Netflix about adoption, <a href="http://www.theadoptedlife.com/">The Adopted Life</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/AngelaMBarra">Angela Barra</a> has recently crossed my path, and I’m looking forward to following her blog, <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/author/angela-barra">Adoptee Reflections</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/iamadopted">Jessenia Arias</a> created and hosts <a href="http://iamadopted.net/">I am Adopted</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/nicole_soojung">Nicole Chung</a> might be best known right now for co-foundering and editing the still-awesome <a href="http://the-toast.net/">The Toast</a>. She used the platform she had there to also raise issues of adoption, transracial adoption, and racial justice.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/DANakaDAN">Dan</a> is executive producer at the fun and entertaining <a href="https://www.youtube.com/isatv">ISAtv</a>, a YouTube channel about Asian Pacific American culture.</li>
<li><a href="https://landofgazillionadoptees.com/">Land of Gazillion Adoptees</a> is an ezine by and for adult adoptees.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.thelostdaughters.com/">Lost Daughters</a> is a group blog that provides a platform for adult women who were adopted as children.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/mckeekee">Kimberly McKee</a> is a researcher in Adoption Studies.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/mothermade">Mother Made</a> blogs and tweets about being a transracial adoptee and is especially eloquent about the tensions inherit in her complex identity.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/MichelleWPD">Michelle</a> uses social media to talk about both adoption and faith.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/yoonsblur">Mila</a> blogs at Lost Daughters. My family had the opportunity of hearing Mila in person a couple of times, and she’s just as powerful of a voice in real life.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/Karen_Pickell">Karen Pickell</a> is a writer, editor, and advocate. She founded <a href="http://adopteereading.com/">Adoptee Reading</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://johnraible.wordpress.com/">John W. Raible</a> comes at this experience from all sides. He is an adoptive parent, and he researches adoption-related issues. He has been a active and tireless voice for adoptee rights, for the issues raised by transracial adoptees, and for other causes.</li>
</ul>
<p>These people all have amazing voices. Go listen to them.</p>
<p>I’ve certainly left out lots of people here. These are just some (not all!) that have been personally significant to me. If you know of someone I should be listening to, please let me know.</p>
<hr />
<h1 id="history">History</h1>
<ul>
<li>Originally published 30 November 2016.</li>
<li>Updated 18 January 2017.</li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>About the Format</title>
    <link href="http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/notes/about-the-format/index.html" />
    <id>http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/notes/about-the-format/index.html</id>
    <published>2017-01-11T11:52:49Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-11T11:52:49Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve disappeared from here for a bit for the holidays. Family emergencies and celebrations have gotten in the way. Still I’ve been thinking about what I’m trying to do here and how best to accomplish that. Part of what I’m asking myself is <em>what are these things I’m posting here</em>.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Obviously, this seems to be a blog. There’s an <a href="/atom.xml">Atom feed</a>. There’s a <a href="/posts/">reverse-chronological index page</a>. Entries are dated. Hell, it even <em>says</em> “Blog” on the home page and the navigation bar. (Or it does today, anyway.)</p>
<p>But I am thinking about these things a little differently. If I have more to say on a topic, I think I’m just as likely to go edit a page instead of posting a new one.</p>
<p>So maybe it’s really a wiki?</p>
<p>Borrowing from Martin Fowler, I’m leaning toward thinking about this as a cross between a blog and a wiki. He’s called them a <a href="https://www.martinfowler.com/bliki/WhatIsaBliki.html">bliki</a>.</p>
<p>There’s still a lot to fill in, though. I need to think about how to allow readers to navigate through previous versions of posts. I need to think about how to be transparent about changes in a way that doesn’t intrude on the reading experience. I need to think about better ways to navigate through time and across time.</p>
<p>But be warned. Posts are unstable. Words will change.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Thanksgiving: Gratitude, Memorial, and Poetry</title>
    <link href="http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/notes/thanksgiving-gratitude-memorial-and-poetry/index.html" />
    <id>http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/notes/thanksgiving-gratitude-memorial-and-poetry/index.html</id>
    <published>2016-11-27T16:52:33Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-27T16:52:33Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m a bit conflicted by this holiday.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>On the one hand, the original day of “Thanksgiving” was a celebration of a <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/richard-greener/the-true-story-of-thanksg_b_788436.html">massacre</a>, and the original pilgrims aren’t all they are sometimes <a href="https://www.manataka.org/page269.html">cracked up to be</a>. We cannot forget this. Teen Vogue, which has really been kicking it lately, also has this video:</p>
<script async src="//player.cnevids.com/embedjs/51cca0c868f9da9f40000008/video/583353aab57ac3189f00002f.js"></script>
<p>But I’m also all for gratitude.</p>
<p>So threaded around turkey and football, I attempt to hold our past in reverent memory while finding things to be grateful for the present.</p>
<p>And I pray that both the memory of the past and gratitude of the present will guide us into a better future.</p>
<p>(Of course, memory of the past and the present collide in the <a href="https://www.bustle.com/articles/196566-support-the-dakota-pipeline-protests-this-thanksgiving-in-5-ways">Standing Rock protests</a>. Not sure where hope for the future is in this, though.)</p>
<p>Some poems for today:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.onbeing.org/blog/carrie-newcomer-three-gratitudes/8902">Three Gratitudes</a> by Carrie Newcomer.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.caapp.pitt.edu/content/ross-gay-reads-title-poem-catalog-unabashed-gratitude">Catalog of Unabashed Gratitude</a> by Ross Gay.</li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Please Ignore</title>
    <link href="http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/code/please-ignore/index.html" />
    <id>http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/code/please-ignore/index.html</id>
    <published>2016-11-21T15:20:04Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-21T15:20:04Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For those who can’t read titles:</p>
<p>I’ve been interested in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literate_programming">literate programming</a> for a while. I’m interested in the relationship between artificial languages and in how we can program more transparently. Literate programming sites at the margins of that.</p>
<p>I’ve also been playing around with <a href="http://www.purescript.org/">PureScript</a> some. It’s <a href="https://haskell-lang.org/">Haskell</a>, redesigned to remove some warts, that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Source-to-source_compiler">transpiles</a> to JavaScript. So far I haven’t used it very much, but I’d like to work with it more.</p>
<p>So creating the ability to create literate PureScript posts on this blog has been on my todo list for a while. Now that I’ve actually started posting again, I thought I’d get this going. For those who are interested and maybe morbidly curious, the changes are in <a href="https://github.com/erochest/erochest.github.com/compare/212d284670ae3355d5d40b45b11ebdb8c8a8feba...27bd636dbed225b0b803ac58cfc2e041b67943b5">this diff</a>. There are a few moving parts, but mostly I just hand things over to <a href="https://github.com/bodil/pulp">pulp</a> as much as I can.</p>
<p>Since this is a literate post, there are some formailities to get started:</p>
<pre class="purescript"><code>module Main where
import Prelude
import Control.Monad.Eff (Eff)
import Control.Monad.Eff.Console (CONSOLE, log)
import Data.Traversable (traverse)
import DOM (DOM)
import DOM.HTML (window)
import DOM.HTML.Types (htmlDocumentToDocument, htmlDocumentToParentNode)
import DOM.HTML.Window (document)
import DOM.Node.Document (createTextNode)
import DOM.Node.Node (appendChild)
import DOM.Node.NodeList (item)
import DOM.Node.ParentNode (querySelectorAll, QuerySelector)
import DOM.Node.Types (textToNode)
import Data.Newtype (wrap)</code></pre>
<p>(If this all seems a little verbose, I’m using a <em>very</em> low-level interface here. For anything more complicated, you’d want to use a higher-level library.)</p>
<p>There are still some things to do on this:</p>
<ul>
<li>Syntax color highlighting;</li>
<li>The code doesn’t work well with the margins;</li>
<li>The code doesn’t work well with the scalable font sizing.</li>
</ul>
<pre class="purescript"><code>main :: forall e. Eff (console :: CONSOLE, dom :: DOM | e) Unit
main = do
    doc      &lt;-  window &gt;&gt;= document
    greeting &lt;-  textToNode
             &lt;$&gt; createTextNode &quot;Hello sailor!&quot;
             (   htmlDocumentToDocument doc)
    _ &lt;- querySelectorAll (wrap &quot;#please-ignore .please-ignore&quot;)
        (   htmlDocumentToParentNode doc)
        &gt;&gt;= item 0
        &gt;&gt;= traverse (appendChild greeting)
    log &quot;Hello sailor!&quot;</code></pre>
<p>As an added bonus, the scaffolded project created by <a href="https://github.com/bodil/pulp">pulp</a> has a gratuitous <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zork">Zork</a> reference. How could I resist?</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Joy</title>
    <link href="http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/notes/joy/index.html" />
    <id>http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/notes/joy/index.html</id>
    <published>2016-11-17T14:20:17Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-17T14:20:17Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This tweet from the NBA Awards clicked:</p>
<!--more-->
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en">
<p lang="en" dir="ltr">
“Joy is an act of resistance” head of the <a href="https://twitter.com/nationalbook"><span class="citation">@nationalbook</span></a> Foundation <a href="https://twitter.com/likaluca"><span class="citation">@likaluca</span></a> just reminded us <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/NBAwards?src=hash">#NBAwards</a> ✊ also <a href="https://twitter.com/deray"><span class="citation">@deray</span></a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/Luvvie"><span class="citation">@Luvvie</span></a> are here!!
</p>
— Daniel José Older (<span class="citation">@djolder</span>) <a href="https://twitter.com/djolder/status/799077106714034179">November 17, 2016</a>
</blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>It reminded me of these lines from the Wendell Berry poem <a href="http://www.onbeing.org/program/program-passover-and-easter/feature/manifesto-mad-farmer-liberation-front/561">Manifesto: The Mad Farmer Liberation Front</a> (the quote on the bottom of each page is also from this poem):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Expect the end of the world. Laugh.<br/> Laughter is immeasurable. Be joyful<br/> though you have considered all the facts.<br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just as I’m trying to be mindful of beauty, I’d like to be attuned to small acts of resistance and acts of resistance that improve day-to-day life.</p>
<p>But I also must challenge myself not to rest there, but to push toward more direct and obvious resistance as well.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Finding Beauty</title>
    <link href="http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/notes/finding-beauty/index.html" />
    <id>http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/notes/finding-beauty/index.html</id>
    <published>2016-11-15T15:45:29Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-15T15:45:29Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past few months, I’ve cultivated an intentional practice to look for beauty.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Partially I’m trying to be more aware of things around me and their beauty. It’s an amazing, fucked up world.</p>
<p>Wading through email is typically not beautiful. So I’ve subscribed to a couple of email lists that help that. Whenever I open one of these, I take a minute to be present to whatever’s inside.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://writersalmanac.org/">Writer’s Almanac</a> sends me a poem each day. There’s a nice variety of anthology-poetry and newer poetry, although my impression is that it does tend toward less experimental works.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.storypeople.com/">StoryPeople</a> sends a drawing and short-short-short story each day. They’re a joyful little interruption from (and engagement in) life.</li>
</ul>
<p>I’m curious where others look for beauty. Feel free to send me suggestions on Twitter or Facebook, and I’ll post some that stand out to me here.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Pace Yourself</title>
    <link href="http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/notes/pace-yourself/index.html" />
    <id>http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/notes/pace-yourself/index.html</id>
    <published>2016-11-14T02:16:56Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-14T02:16:56Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Four years is a long time. Eight years is longer.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Both those time spans are easy to wrap our heads around, though. The truth is that most of us will be dead before the world sees the kind of society we want to live in.</p>
<p>This isn’t a sprint. It’s not even a marathon. It’s a multigenerational migration.</p>
<p>I’ll be posting links to more humor, trying my hand at more fiction. I’ll be trying to listen to those who’ve worked these fields before me.</p>
<p>Pace yourself.</p>
<hr />
<p>I was going to pull a quote or two from each of these links, but they’re both just so good. At some point this week I’m going to highlight quotes I like from the transcripts of these on <a href="https://hypothes.is/">Hypothesis</a>. Those will probably show up again on this blog in some form.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.onbeing.org/program/parker-palmer-and-courtney-martin-the-inner-life-of-rebellion/7122">The Inner Life of Rebellion</a> — Parker Palmer and Courtney Martin</li>
<li><a href="http://www.onbeing.org/program/vincent-harding-is-america-possible/79">Is America Possible?</a> — Vincent Harding</li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Read It!</title>
    <link href="http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/notes/read-it/index.html" />
    <id>http://www.ericrochester.com//posts/notes/read-it/index.html</id>
    <published>2016-11-12T12:33:59Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-12T12:33:59Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Read this whole thread:</p>
<!--more-->
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en">
<p lang="en" dir="ltr">
I woke up out of my dead sleep an hour ago. I knew Trump won before I went to bed. I just thought I might have a full nights sleep first
</p>
— 5'7 Black Male (<span class="citation">@absurdistwords</span>) <a href="https://twitter.com/absurdistwords/status/796301496698671104">November 9, 2016</a>
</blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
